Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Levinson, Louis, 1974 February 25 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 124 a-b, Box 34, Reel 121a - 121b)
    Louis Levinson was born in Staryya Darohi in the Minsk region of Russia in 1907 to a Jewish family. His father immigrated to the United States before World War I and Levinson, his mother, and his sister immigrated in 1923. Levinson entered the knitting industry in the mid-1920s in order to support his family. He worked as a cutter and was quickly promoted to head cutter. He was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 155 until his retirement in 1972.
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz on February 25, 1975 at the offices of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) in Manhattan, New York. The main topics include Louis Levinson's emigration from the Soviet Union; his work in the garment industry; and his involvement with the ILGWU Local 155. Levinson discusses his difficulty emigrating from the Soviet Union, including leaving his mother and sister behind to walk to the border of the Soviet Union and Poland; having to bribe Bolshevik border guards with his mother's watch; sending for his mother and sister after he arrived in Poland; and his mother being shot by the Bolshevik guards. He recalls his family being arrested in Poland for being in the country illegally; receiving valid passports with the help of the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society of America; and the anti-Semitism the family encountered in Poland. He recalls his early experiences in the United States (US) including working in a dry goods store; quitting his job in order to attend a private school; his father having a stroke, leaving Levinson the sole earner of the household; and finding a job in the knitting industry.
    Levinson discusses his work as a cutter and his involvement in labor unions, including failed attempts at unionization within the knitting industry until 1933; the fight between the United Textile Workers Union and the ILGWU for control of the knitting industry; and his involvement in the ILGWU after answering a newspaper advertisement looking for members. He recalls being elected to a provisional committee at his first ILGWU meeting and increasing the number of knitting workers in attendance by asking everyone to bring a new attendee to each meeting. He discusses his political involvement within his local including being a member of the executive board; holding nearly every office and being a member of every committee; being elected as the business agent in 1943; being re-elected in every election until he retired in 1972; and feeling extremely proud that he was able to influence the knitting industry through his work in the ILGWU.
    Labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.
  - Levitino, Frank, 1974 April 9 (Box 101, Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 155, Box 34, Reel 122a, Box 1, Folder 54)
    Frank Levitino was born in a small town in Sicily, Italy around 1904. His father immigrated to the United States (US) a year after Levitino was born. Levitino and his mother immigrated to the US in 1921. The family lived lived on York and Main Streets in the Fulton Landing neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. In Italy, he and his mother worked on a farm. In the US, his mother did not work outside of the home. His father cleaned in a factory. Levitino's first two jobs in the US were in a can factory on Front Street in Brooklyn and in a sugar factory. He served in the United States Army Coast Artillery Corps for one year in the early 1920s. In 1927 he started working for the New York City Department of Sanitation, driving a truck and working as a welder in the mechanic bureau. He was a member of the International Union of Operating Engineers. He retired in 1972.
    Levitino married in 1930 and had three children. The family lived in the same building as Levitino's parents in Fulton Landing.
    This interview was conducted by Joan Granucci on April 9, 1974. The location is likely the Congress of Italian Americans Organization (CIAO) in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Frank Levitino's working life the United States (US) and his family. Levitino discusses his first jobs in the US, including the fact that the change from farm work to factory work did not bother him; that he was happy to be in America and have a job; and the poor working conditions and lack of unions in the factories. He discusses his work for the New York City Department of Sanitation, including first driving a truck; testing to become a welder in the mechanic bureau; and repairing motor blocks. He discusses failed attempts at unionization in the Department of Sanitation and the success of the International Union of Operating Engineers in 1966.
    Sanitation workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Welders (Persons) |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Sanitation; International Union of Operating Engineers
  - Lewis, George, Undated (Box Missing, Box 1, Folder 99)
    George Lewis was born in Mobile, Alabama in 1897. He had two siblings and five half-siblings. His father worked as a carpenter in Mobile and for the American Car and Foundry Company in St. Louis, Missouri, and his mother worked as a cook for a wealthy family in Mobile. He attended elementary school up to the seventh grade. He worked at an unspecified sawmill, repair shop, and railroad in Alabama; at the Alabama Drydock Shipbuilding Company; at the Sun Shipyard in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and at the Baltimore Locomotive Works in Eddystone, Pennsylvania. While in Detroit, Michigan, he worked for the Dodge Brothers Company and for the Chrysler Corporation. He migrated to New York, New York in 1922 and settled in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. While in New York, he worked at the Pioneer Knitting Mill as a presser; at an unspecified company as an assistant stationary engineer; at a company that manufactured clamshell buckets; and at the Russell Sage Foundation.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. The audio recording for this interview is missing. This interview covers George Lewis's childhood in Alabama; his migrations to Pennsylvania, Michigan, and New York; and his life and work at each of these locations. Lewis begins by discussing a lack of education in the United States (US), noting that many schools excluded black children and poor children. He recalls having a doctor create a fake birth certificate and a friend teach him the appropriate technical knowledge so that he could work on the railroad. He describes a series of migrations after he left the railroad, noting that he went from the southern US to the northern US and back again before realizing that he could no longer tolerate the racism in his hometown and leaving for good in 1920. Lewis describes migrating to New York, New York in 1922, recalling that he did not have any family in New York and that he had to pursue different lines of work because employers were wary of hiring black employees in the mechanical fields. Other topics include descriptions of his jobs and wages; the impact of segregation on the various places in which he lived and traveled; his leisure activities in New York; anecdotes about how he developed his skills; his recollections concerning labor unions; and his experiences with politics and religion.
    See also: Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast.
  - Lewis, Ivan, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 217, 217a, Box 35, Reel 124a - 124b)
    Ivan Lewis was born in Port of Spain, Trinidad and Tobago in 1903. He immigrated to the United States and settled in New York, New York. In New York City, Lewis married and worked in steel plants, a slaughterhouse, and for an elevator company. He was a member of an unspecified elevator operators' union.
    Ivan Lewis was interviewed at his home in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The date and interviewer are unknown. Main topics of discussion include Lewis' life in Trinidad and Tobago; his social life in New York City between the 1930s and the time of the interview; and politics at the time of the interview. Lewis discusses his early life in Trinidad and Tobago, including his family being wealthy and his father owning three estates; his father dying when Lewis was six; having three sisters and one brother; and attending high school. He mentions his immigration to the United States, including his first impressions of New York City; immigrating in order to continue his education; living with his aunt in Manhattan until he married in 1927; attending night school to become an auto mechanic; and being in awe of the New York City Subway and elevators. He discusses his participation in the social scene and leisure activities in New York City, including attending the Cotton Club every Thursday; socializing with his neighbors on the street and in cafes. He also recalls the existence of a large West Indian community in both Brooklyn and Harlem. He lists former employers, including Eastern Foundry in Trinidad and Tobago; and in the US, working for an unnamed spring manufacturer; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; and Wilson Slaughterhouse in Manhattan, New York. He discusses working as an elevator operator until his retirement. Lewis mentions that he was a member of an unnamed elevator operators' union and that the strikes were never violent. He discusses politics at the time of the interview including feeling disillusioned with politics; supporting Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. and thinking Powell was killed because of his influence in the community; and believing that the events of the Watergate Scandal were not uncommon within politics.
    See also: Family; Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States; and Neighborhood.
    Elevator operators |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Cotton Club
  - Life Before Immigration or Migration, Undated (Box 75, Reel 334a - 334b)
    This recording contains excerpts of different interviews, all of which focus on discussions of immigrants' and migrants' lives before they came to New York, New York. The volume and sound quality of this recording fluctuate between excerpts. The excerpts include discussion of life in the narrators' places of origin, including education, social and economic conditions, ethnic relations, class differences, major occupations, and the differences in opportunities for men and women. A significant number of narrators address the Jewish experience, including the relationship between Jewish communities living alongside other religious communities in the same area; and anti-Semitism before and during World War II. Narrators also discuss their reasons for immigration or migration and the sequence of family members' immigration or migration.
    See also: Brackett, Mary; Cappeletti, Caroline Lavecchia; Cohen, Rose; Fox, Abe; Geller, Bessie; Gelo, Grace; Prescant, Becky; Richards, Evadni; Robinson, Irene; Savio, Joseph; Sunderman, [Unknown]; and Unger, Margareta.
  - Little, Mary, 1976 April 4 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 208, Box 35, Reel 125a - 125b)
    Mary Little was born on January 1, 1924 in Washington, North Carolina. She was the second of four children. Her parents worked in a tobacco warehouse in Greenwood, North Carolina. Her father died when Little was very young. Little graduated from high school in Washington. She moved to New York, New York in 1945, where she worked in various garment factories. She had two children, a daughter who became a registered nurse and a son who became an actor and a dancer.
    This interview was conducted by Nina Cobb at Mary Little's home on the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York on April 4, 1976. This interview covers Little's childhood and adolescence in Washington, North Carolina, her migration to New York, New York in 1945, and her life in New York City up to the time of the interview. Little describes her childhood as split between Washington, where she was born, and the family's farm, which her mother inherited from her grandfather, a former slave. She discusses her work tending to cotton and peanut plants on the family farm and the differences in the chores she and her brothers were assigned. She describes her first job attending to the mother of a Mrs. Legette, a member of a prominent white family in Washington. She focuses on how she integrated with the family, noting that Mrs. Legette threatened to withdraw her membership from the local Presbyterian church if it did not allow Little to attend with the family. She discusses the open racial prejudice and segregation that permeated the southern United States (US); the jobs her brothers acquired; her marriage; and her desire to visit New York.
    Little explains that she moved to New York in 1945 and adapted to Manhattan while living with her relatives. She describes working in a variety of garment factories, always moving on to a new factory when she had learned everything she could at the old one. She emphasizes the differences between living in the northern and southern United States, noting the differences in the ways that men treated women; the differences in family values; and the differences between living in the southern countryside and living in a northern city. Little ends the interview by talking about her children's occupations, focusing specifically on her son's acting career.
  - Loskowitz, Charles, 1973 March 21 and March 26 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 22-23, Box 35, Reel 127a, Box 36, Reel 127b - 127d, Box 1, Folder 55)
    Charles Loskowitz was born in Russia in the 1890s. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1904 with his mother and two siblings, his father and two older siblings having immigrated earlier. The family settled in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. His father worked as a carpenter in Russia and as a presser in a dress factory in the US. His mother did not work outside the home. Loskowitz graduated from Public School 156 in Brooklyn and worked while attending a private high school. He worked in the Canadian Car and Foundry Company's ammunition plant in New Jersey until it was destroyed in 1917. He worked for Remington Arms in Bridgeport, Connecticut. He joined the US Army in 1917 and was stationed in England, France, and Germany. He was discharged at the end of World War I.
    Loskowitz worked as a letter carrier for the United States Postal Service for 27 years, retiring in 1946. He was a member of the National Association of Letter Carriers and the American Legion. He married in 1917. He and his wife had three children before divorcing in the 1940s.
    This interview was conducted by Mary B. Alexander at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York on March 21 and March 26, 1973. The interview covers Charles Loskowitz's childhood in Russia and the United States (US), his immigration to the US, his working life, and his marriage. Loskowitz compares his life in Russia with his life in US, including his surprise at the differences in the family's living arrangements; his confusion over laundry hanging outdoors on clotheslines; and his experiences at school. He discusses his work at the Canadian Car and Foundry Company's munitions plant in New Jersey; the explosion at the plant in 1917; and his recuperation at a stranger's home.
    Loskowitz discusses not being interested in joining immigrant organizations but in organizations related to his experiences in the US, in particular his occupation as a letter carrier and his Army service during World War I which led to his joining the National Association of Letter Carriers and the American Legion. He discusses his marriage at length, describing his unhappiness in the marriage; the arrangement of the marriage by his mother and her cousin; and his children's relationship with him and his wife after the divorce. He describes his wife changing her and their children's last name to Laskoe in order to Americanize it and his neutral feelings about this change. He explains reasons immigrants would change their names once in the US.
    Other topics include his children and their occupations; his opinions on Judaism and Catholicism; sports he played as a child; and songs he would sing with his family around the dinner table.
    Divorce |z United States |v Anecdotes.; Kingsland Explosion, Lyndhurst, N.J., 1917; National Association of Letter Carriers (U.S.)
  - Lynch, Gwendaline, 1974 April 9 (Box Missing, Box 1, Folder 100)
    Gwendaline Lynch was born on October 26, 1900 in Jamaica. Her father was a minister, and her mother was a teacher. She graduated from high school in Jamaica. She immigrated to Colombia where she worked as a secretary and taught English to children in her home. After contracting malaria, she returned to Jamaica before immigrating to the United States (US) in 1921. She settled on 7th Avenue and West 142nd Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She worked in the garment industry, for the federal government, and as a secretary and stenographer for Marcus Garvey. She married in 1925 and had four children.
    This interview was conducted by Cenen Moreno on April 9, 1974, at an unknown location. The audio recording for this interview is missing. This interview covers Gwendaline Lynch's childhood and early adult life in Jamaica and Colombia; her immigration to the United States (US) in 1921; and her work for and relationship with Marcus Garvey. Lynch describes her childhood and education in Jamaica. She discusses her immigration to Colombia after graduating from St. John's College and Preparatory School and her decision to live near her step-sister and her husband. She describes her work as a secretary for a prestigious banker and how his competitors tried to poach her while he was away. She explains that she did not encounter racial prejudice in Colombia, but that there were distinctions along gender and class lines and that she was viewed as different because it was not customary for women to work. She explains that she returned to Jamaica when she contracted malaria and from there immigrated to the United States (US) in 1921, originally intending to stay only six months.
    Lynch recalls being astounded by racial prejudice in the US and relates the differences between people's behavior in the US and in Colombia. She describes living with her aunt on 7th Avenue and West 142nd Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and meeting her first Jamaican friend at St. Philip's Church in Harlem. She explains that she first met Marcus Garvey in Jamaica and that she became his secretary and stenographer in New York after attending one of his meetings there. She describes Garvey's ideology and philosophy; the problems with developing and implementing the Black Star Line, particularly the first voyage of the Yarmouth; tension between Garvey's idealist views and the mercenary tendencies of those that worked for him; his relationship with W.E.B. DuBois and Booker T. Washington; and his arrest for mail fraud, trial, and subsequent time in jail. She explains that she left Garvey's organization before she married in 1925. She discusses her career after her marriage, including working for a broker in Harlem, for a dress business, and for the federal government during World War II. Other topics include teaching English to children in Colombia; political disputes and the impact they had on the Colombian people; a secretarial business she established with some friends in New York; her children's education and occupations; and a comparison of the situation of the black population in the US in the past and at the time of the interview.
    Secretaries -- New York (State) -- New York; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Colombia.; Garvey, Marcus, 1887-1940
  - M., Flora, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 239, Box 44, Reel 332b/150a, Box 100, Cassette 150)
    Flora M. was born in Ponce, Puerto Rico and was the fifth of many children. The full surname of this interviewee is unknown. Her father was a meat merchant and her mother managed the household. Flora migrated to the United States when she was 13 years old, joining her sister who had migrated earlier. She worked as a dressmaker predominantly doing piecework and was a member of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 22. She married and had one daughter.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. The second track of the interview is entirely in Spanish. This interview covers Flora M.'s childhood in Puerto Rico; her migration to the United States; her early years in New York; and cultural and environmental differences she observes between New York and Puerto Rico. Flora describes her childhood in Ponce, Puerto Rico and explains that she migrated to New York when she was 13 at the request of her sister, who had migrated earlier. She recalls that she would have remained in Puerto Rico but that her mother sent her, despite her desire to stay, and that this created a rift between them. She explains that the rest of her family eventually migrated to New York in search of economic security. She recounts attending high school at night in New York and notes that few of the Puerto Rican students took their education seriously. She briefly describes learning dressmaking; working on piecework; and joining Local 22 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
    Flora explains that she married a significantly older man in order to escape her sister's strict rules. She focuses on her initial experiences in New York, describing the poverty that forced her to look through the garbage to find food during the Great Depression and her acclimation to winter in New York. She emphasizes the decline in the importance of religion for some Puerto Ricans after they migrated to New York, observing that many of her family members went to church less and less frequently once they were in New York.
    Puerto Ricans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.)
  - Magliacano, Joseph, 1973 March 27 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 146, Box 36, Reel 130a - 130b, Box 1, Folder 56)
    Joseph Magliacano was born on July 11, 1897 in San Marco in the province of Salerno, Italy. He immigrated to the United States in 1913. He lived in the Bronx, New York; the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York; and Newark, New Jersey. He graduated from an unspecified chiropractic college in New York City (likely the Carver Chiropractic College) in 1924. He was a member of the American Labor Party, an unspecified barbers' union in New York, and the executive committee of the New Jersey State Congress of Industrial Organizations. He was an organizer for a number of labor unions, including the United Textile Workers of America and the United Shoe Workers' Union. He was a founder of the United Furniture Workers of America and remained with that organization until his retirement.
    Magliacano married in 1931. His wife was Jewish and was born in Bronxville, New York. She was a member of the United Shoe Workers Union and an organizer for an unspecified Jewish women's organization. They had at least one child together.